Finding Aid for Calvin O. Davis papers, 1910-1941
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Calvin O. Davis papers 1910-1941
Davis, Calvin Olin, 1871-
2 linear feet
851254 Aa 2
Professor of education at University of Michigan. Correspondence, diary of European trip (1931), manuscripts, lecture notes and articles.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Calvin O. Davis (donor no. 1973 ) and came to the library in 1944.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Calvin O. Davis was born Feb. 5, 1871, at Macomb, Mich., a son of Calvin and Roselia Phillips Davis. He received his bachelor's degree from the University of Michigan in 1895 and his master's degree in 1904. He received a Ph.D. degree from Harvard in 1910. While working on his advanced degrees, Davis also taught school in South Bend, Ind. He joined the faculty of the University in 1905 as an instructor in education and inspector of high schools. He was made a professor of education in 1915. When the School of Education was organized in 1921, Davis became its secretary, a position which he held until his 1941 retirement.
Davis was a member of the National Education Association, the National Society of Scientific Study of Education, the Society of College Teachers of Education and the Michigan State Teachers' Association. He also belonged to the Phi Beta Kappa and Phi Delta Kappa societies. He was the author of several books, including the "History of the North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools." He died June 22, 1954.
The bulk of the Davis collection consists of manuscripts, lecture notes and articles. Included is his manuscript autobiography entitled "A Country Lad" and "History of the Ann Arbor Rotary Club." The lectures are on educational topics. In addition, the collection has correspondence largely relating to University of Michigan and School of Education affairs, and a diary of a trip to Europe in 1931.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Rotary Club.; Congregational Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; First Congregational Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Travelers.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Davis, Calvin Olin, 1871-
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Correspondence, lecture materials, and writings
  - Correspondence, 1913-1923 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1941 (Box 1)
  - Diary of Trip Abroad, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Lecture Outlines (Box 1)
  - Lectures on Curriculum Topics, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Lectures on Junior High School, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Lectures on Teacher Training Problems, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous articles and lectures, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Courses (Box 1)
  - Historical topics, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Toasts (Box 1)
  - Retirement (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - History of the Ann Arbor Rotary Club, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Article "University and College Accrediting" (Box 1)
  - Problems of the High School Curriculum (Box 1)
  - Problems of the Junior High School (Box 1)
  - History of the First Congregational Church (Box 1)
  - "A Country Lad" by C.D. Davis (Box 1)
  - Papers, addresses and studies of Calvin O. Davis, 1910-1930, 3 volumes (Box 2)
  - Doctoral thesis, Harvard University, 1910 entitled, "Public Secondary Education in Michigan" (Box 2)